Finding Aid for Marvin M. Meerse papers, 1943-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marvin M. Meerse papers 1943-1978
Meerse, Marvin M., 1910-1978.
1 linear foot
861116 Aa 2
Career army officer, speechwriter for military and political figures on army-related topics. Speeches, diaries, 1971 and 1973, copy of his mystery novel, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Ada Sager (donor no. 7171 ), the sister of Marvin Meerse, 1985.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Marvin M. Meerse (1910-1978) served in the U.S. Army from 1943 to 1970. After combat duty in the Philippines during World War II, much of his time was spent teaching public speaking and military psychology in the Adjutant General's School. From 1955 until his retirement, he was speechwriter for several of the Army's top generals in Europe and Korea. In June 1963, one of his speeches was read by President Kennedy to U.S. forces in Hanau, West Germany. Meerse was also a writer for several Army publications and editor of Gimmicks and Gadgets. Upon his retirement, Meerse had achieved the rank of Sergeant Major.
After he left the service, Meerse devoted much of his time to railroad clubs. He served as president and editor of the Cincinnati Railroad Club and in 1975 published Richmond Junction, a mystery novel with a railroad setting.
The papers of Marvin M. Meerse consist of one linear foot of material and cover the years 1943-1978. Though the collection includes both professional and personal papers, the vast majority of the papers are professional, mostly texts of speeches written by Meerse from 1955 to 1968.
As these speeches are often discussions of freedom, containment, and the threat of communism, they provide insight into the soldier's perspective on these topics. Included in the collection are speeches written by Meerse for generals: A.C. McAuliffe, Bruce C. Clarke, Paul Freeman, Dwight Beach, C.H. Bonisteel, Creighton W. Abrams, Jr., George T. Duncan, Louis W. Truman, and W.C. Garrison. There is also a speech written by Meerse and delivered by President John Kennedy and speeches by Attorney General Robert Kennedy and Secretary of the Army Wilber Brucker, presumably also written by Meerse.
Subjects:
Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; Meerse, Marvin M., 1910-1978.; Speech.; United States. Army.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Germany.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Korea (South); Meerse, Marvin M., 1910-1978.; Military camps.; Military inspections.; Military officers.; Speechwriting.; United States. Army.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Professional Papers
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - General A.C. McAuliffe, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - Several persons, 1957-1963 (Box 1)
      (includes speech for John Kennedy; also speeches by Wilber Brucker and Robert Kennedy)
    - Generals Truman, Duncan, and Garrison, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - General Paul Freeman, 1960-1965 (Box 1)
    - Generals Freeman and Bruce Clarke, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
      (bound volume also contains 1963 speech by President Kennedy)
    - Several persons, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
    - Graduation and commencement, 1950-1961 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Aptitude tests and humorous bits (Box 1)
  - Greetings and congratulatory messages
    - Generals Clarke and Freeman, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
    - Generals Dwight Beach, C.H. Bonisteel, and others, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Posters and flyers, NCO Club No. 1, 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed (Box 1)
- Personal Papers
  - 1950-1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971-1978 (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1971 and 1973 (Box 1)
  - Richmond Junction 1975 (Box 1)
    (railroad novel by Meerse)
  - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 1)